Okay all right. Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. Today's דף daf
is פ"ו, Pe-Vav, 86. We pick up in the משנה Mishnah on
פ"ה עמוד ב. Pe-He Amud Bet. גוט מועד, Gut Moed, and we
are moving on to חנק. Henek. So we did somebody who smites
mother and father and now we get on to the next one:
הגונב נפש מישראל, Hagonev Nefesh miYisrael, so somebody who kidnaps. Now kidnapping,
when we hear of kidnapping, we primarily think about ransom. Exactly, thank
you. But in the פסוקים pesukim kidnapping was, you know, basically about
stealing somebody as a slave. I mean, if you think about it,
the whole slave trade in America, right, mostly happened as a result
of wars in Africa. Not only wars, I mean, because like
Africans were involved in the slave trade as well at the supply
side, not only as being the slaves but as supplying the slaves
and as actually raiding other tribes and capturing people and then selling
them, you know. So sometimes it would be a byproduct of war,
sometimes it would be specifically let's capture this person. I mean, think
about the יוסף Yosef story, right. You know, what do the brothers
do, right? They captured him. I mean, that's the whole אלה אזכרה
Elleh Ezkerah that we say and then sold him off as a
slave. So that's the classic
example in the תורה, Torah, which by the way, just
in גיטין, Gittin, there's a whole discussion about one of the things
that they did for תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam was that they said
you cannot pay exorbitant amounts to redeem a captive because then it
would just, you know, sort of like negotiating with terrorists, it would
just sort of
encourage people to go ahead and to seize captives again.
And the limit was set at you can't pay יותר מכדי דמיהן,
yoter mikedei demaihen, more than their standard value. What's a standard value?
Like we think about today's phenomenon of like somebody kidnaps, God forbid,
a child and asks the parents for millions of dollars. What's כדי
דמיהן? kedei demaihen? So כדי דמיהן kedei demaihen meant the slave market.
Right? So if somebody is taken captive and they want to sell
them back to you at the normal slave market price, that would
be allowed. But if they're asking an exorbitant amount, that's going to
feed into this other phenomenon, this ransom phenomenon. And at least according
to that משנה Mishnah you're not supposed to do it. Over there
in גיטין, Gittin, of course then תוספות Tosafot raises the question, I
mean, let's say it's a family member, other types of issues. I
don't want to go in there but I just want to lay
the scene that the classic example of stealing a person is basically
to sell them as a slave. So anyway, so here it says,
so the פסוק pasuk says, כי ימצא איש גנב נפש מאחיו מבני
ישראל והתעמר בו ומכרו ומת הגנב ההוא. ki yimatze ish gonev nefesh
me'achiv mibnei Yisrael vehitamer bo umacharo umet haganav hahu. If somebody is
found stealing a fellow Jew and using... והתעמר בו vehitamer bo is
interpreted by the גמרא Gemara as makes use of him, you know,
and then sells him, then that גנב ganav will be put to
death. So סתם מיתה stam mita is חנק. henek. And that has
three definitions there: stealing, selling, and this other thing of והתעמר בו,
vehitamer bo, which is a criteria but it's sort of seen as
a sort of less of a dominant part of the act. The
act of basically stealing and selling with this condition that he has
to actually have been used as a slave by the person who
stole him. So let's take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. הגונב
נפש מישראל אינו חייב עד שיכניסנו לרשותו. Hagonev nefesh miYisrael eino chayav
ad sheyachnisenu lirshuto.
You have to first of all the גנב ganav has to have
taken him. גנב נפש מאחיו מבני ישראל Gonev nefesh me'achiv mibnei Yisrael
has to take him into his domain under his control. Now that's
normal גניבה, gneivah, right, is that, is that you have to do
some act of קנין kinyan taking into your control.
The question here is on the one hand, this is a חידוש
chidush because like you can't do a קנין kinyan on a person,
on a free person. So on the one hand that we do
set up the similar formal requirements that you have to do some
type of a מעשה קנין. ma'aseh kinyan. But it doesn't just say
a מעשה קנין. ma'aseh kinyan. If I'm going and I'm stealing Michael's
sheep and I steal into his yard and I lift up his
sheep, I'm a גנב ganav even though I haven't taken it off
the ground because that's a מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan that shows control.
Here the phrase is עד שיכניסנו לרשותו. ad sheyachnisenu lirshuto. And some
of the ראשונים Rishonim actually say that maybe it's not enough to
lift the person up, you know, maybe specifically it's because it says
like, גנב נפש מבני ישראל gonev nefesh mibnei Yisrael somehow there's somehow
of taking somebody, it's not just an act of קנין. kinyan. An
act of קנין kinyan as we said is not exactly doesn't actually
fit, you know, you don't do קנינים kinyanim on people that aren't
already slaves.
Right, possibly. Exactly, from your house, until רשות הרבים reshut harabbim and
put you in your
house, right?
Correct, correct. It might actually require me because, you know, it's also
an interesting question. Like if I go ahead and I take somebody
and I lift him up and then I in the middle of
the street, you know, and then I see you and I say
you want to buy this little slave boy? And you pay me
for him or whatever, right? So obviously I've done a horrific thing.
I mean, nobody's questioning that. But how much did I steal him
or how much did I just have this little boy following me,
right,
and you're the one then that took him and you took him
away to your, to your plantation or wherever you took him? So
the idea is again, how do you define what it means to
steal a person? So the requirement is that I actually have to
bring it into your domain. And again as I said, according to
some ראשונים Rishonim a מעשה קניין Maaseh Kinyan lifting up might not
be enough. רבי יהודה אומר עד שיכניסנו לרשותו וישתמש בו. Rabbi Yehuda
omer ad sheyachnisenu lreshuto vyishtamesh bo. So it sounds like they're debating
whether this idea of using him is an actual requirement. Stealing and
selling is dominant, dominates in the פסוק. pasuk. How do you understand
this requirement of והתעמר בו? vhitamer bo? So Rabbi Yehuda says yes,
yes, you have to use him. שנאמר והתעמר בו Shene'emar vhitamer bo
and he makes use of
him ומכרו. umekharo. Okay, הגונב את בנו. Hagoniv es beno.
Now let's say somebody steals his own son and sells his own
son off as a slave, right, which is a little interesting because
a person
can let's say it doesn't matter, I mean you're חייב chayav whether
you steal an adult or a minor. But a father can actually
sell his daughter as a slave if she's a minor but not
his son. So let's say he goes ahead and does it. רבי
ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yishmael bno shel Rabbi
Yochanan ben Beroka מחייב, mechayiv, you're חייב, chayav, וחכמים פוטרים vachachamim potrin
and the חכמים chachamim exempt and we'll see why, but basically because
it's like not taking something it's well we'll see in the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, גנב מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין. ganev mi shechetzyo
eved vechetzyo ben chorin. Rabbi Yehuda מחייב mechayiv וחכמים פוטרים. vachachamim potrin.
You sell somebody, you know that movie right, 12 years a slave,
right, which is a person who was sold as a free man
who was sold as a slave because he was black and he
could be claimed to be a slave. So if you steal somebody's
slave and sell it, you're not חייב chayav because you know that
person you haven't enslaved that person, you've taken them away from their
original master and sold them to another master, right, but you haven't
enslaved this person. Okay, but if you actually take somebody, it has
to be a free man. What if it's somebody who's חציו עבד
וחציו בן חורין, chetzyo eved vechetzyo ben chorin, right, owned by partners,
one partner freed him or whatever. How much are you חייב? chayav?
He's now fully enslaved them but they weren't fully free to begin
with. Okay, so here the משנה Mishnah says that that's a debate.
Rabbi Yehuda says you're חייב chayav and חכמים chachamim say you're exempt.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Yes?
What happens to the person who buys it? Is he also liable?
The person who buys it, like so that, the person who buys
it is not liable the death penalty. Now we're presuming that the
person who buys it is like is unwitting, thinks that you're the
actual owner, right? It's an interesting question that if the person who
buys it knows that you stole this person and then they also
I imagine that if that were true, it's a very interesting question,
I don't know the answer off the top of my head, I
would just intuitively say that that person would also be עובר over
on having stolen somebody because if I took this little kid that
you had stolen and I knew he was stolen and I was
taking him, I was also stealing him, taking a free person, enslaving
him and making him a slave. Okay, but I would not be
חייב chayav for having sold him. Like I participated, I was מסייע,
mesayaya, you're עבירה, aveira, I would have transgressed the prohibition of stealing.
We're going to see in the גמרא Gemara that there's two prohibitions:
don't steal and then don't sell the slave you stole. Only if
you transgress both do you get the death penalty. But transgressing either
one is still a prohibition, right? So okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: ותנא קמא לא בעי אימור? vtanna kamma lo
baey imur? How could it be that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
going into this debate of stealing, and Rabbi Yehuda says no, no,
you have to use him. How could the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
not require that? It's explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. So אמר רבי
אחא בריה דרבא, Amar Rabbi Acha brei deRava, אימור פחות משווה פרוטה
איכא בינייהו. imur pachos misheveh prutah ika beinaihu. No, no, the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says it doesn't have to be a שווה פרוטה's
shaveh prutah worth of use. You know, you can just like I
don't know, rest your arm on him, you know, something that isn't
even worth a פרוטה. prutah. There just has to be some degree
of use. And Rabbi Yehuda says it has to be a פרוטה's
prutah worth. And the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens like the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. Now the question is what is the logic that you
have to use him, right? If the problem is I took a
free person, I stole them away, I sold them off, right, they're
never going to get back to their parents and so on, right,
or I'm imagining it's a kid, I mean you can steal an
adult as well, like I said like that whole movie 12 years
a slave. But anyway what's the idea of having to use him?
Why is that relevant? I mean it's not like, you know, it
might be like you might want to say that the purchaser has
to use him, has to enslave him, but why me? But like
my feeling about this would be that the idea is that it's
not so much the transgression but it gives context and meaning to
what I did, right? Like what does it mean that I turned
a free person into a slave? Right, if I just like picked
up this kid, right, this kid like I saw on the street
and I walked him to my house and then I sold him
off to somewhere, did I turn him into a slave? I sold
him to somebody else who was going to enslave him, right? So
I was involved in the slave trade, right, but if I actually
make use of him, right, and therefore I therefore am part of
the one who has transformed him and enslaved him. So that's what
I see the significance is of this requirement of not only stealing
and selling but actually making use of the person, because that makes
the גנב gannav also the person who's transforming him into a slave,
who's defining him as a slave, who's enslaving him. Okay, that's my
understanding of the significance of this אימור. imur. Okay. So and that's
why even less than a שווה פרוטה, shaveh prutah, because it doesn't
really matter that you like stole something of monetary value from this
person, what matters is that you created that context of treating him
as a slave, right, of making him a slave. Okay. So now
בעי רבי ירמיה, Baey Rabbi Yirmiyah, and now Rabbi Yirmiyah asked,
גנבו ומכרו ישן... ganavo umekharo yashan... מכר אשה לעוברה מהו. Machar isha
le'ubarrah mahu. If a woman is sold for her for her fetus,
okay, a man steals a woman who's pregnant, sells her to somebody
else and says, I am selling you the fetus, but I retain
ownership over the woman. Okay, so has he now, is that stealing
and selling? Okay, so because you know, sold someone, the thing, right,
what was sold, the fetus doesn't yet have an independent identity. Right,
you know, and it's גונב נפש מאחיו מבני ישראל gonev nefesh me'achav
miBnei Yisrael like we sort of said before, what has to be
sold is a born person. Okay, it doesn't have to be an
adult, but what has to be stolen and sold has to be
a born person. So you're not חייב chayav for stealing the fetus,
you're חייב chayav for stealing the woman. But then you didn't sell
the woman, you only sold her for the purpose of the fetus.
Okay, so what would be that story? To me the first one
should be חייב chayav and the second one should be פטור, patur,
not morally, but just in terms of the formal definition of the
פסוק. pasuk. Right, it's hard to understand why if the guy is
asleep that should mean that you're חייב chayav that you'd be
פטור. patur. יש דרך עימור בכך או אין דרך עימור בכך, yesh
derech imur bekach o ein derech imur bekach, it's a very funny
way of framing the question. Is this considered a normal way to
make use of something or not? How do you use a person?
Well, you use a sleeping person by lying on them or reclining
on them. But why, but yeah, but right, but why is that
the issue? Right, the question is about the selling, right, not about
like, you know, the רמב"ם Rambam says if somebody you stole somebody
asleep and you leaned on them, and then you sold them when
they were awake, you'd be חייב. chayav. So the עימור imur criteria
is only a minor middle point in the, you know, in the
middle. And the person could be asleep, or if you steal a
pregnant woman and you make use of her, you have her, I
don't know, you know, mix you a drink or something like that,
and then you sell her לעוברה, le'ubarrah, so the עימור imur requirement
was satisfied. So the real question is, is it considered a legitimate
sale? Right, why is it being framed as a type, is there
this עימור imur or not עימור, imur, is very unclear to me.
Okay, let's read what the גמרא Gemara says.
I know, the גמרא Gemara never even spells out what the question
is about being asleep. Let's read. Okay. Is that the way of
doing the עימור imur or not? ותיבא ליה דליכא עימור כלל, veteba
lei dileka imur klal, so the גמרא Gemara says well, how are
you using this person anyway? The sleeping person, that's presumably what it's
asking. Pregnant woman is obvious. So it says look, צריכא, tsricha, no,
no, I can give you a way in which you're using them.
ישן דזגא עליה, yashen dizaga aleih, if somebody is sleeping, you lie
on them, you know, you make use of them that way,
עליה. aleih. אשה, Isha, a pregnant woman, דאוקמה באפי זיקא. de'ukma be'apei
zika. You ever stand to protect you from the wind? Now that's
silly, why doesn't it just say like I said, you have her,
I don't know, tie your shoes, pour you a drink? So it
seems like what we want is we want the fetus to be
used. So because she's pregnant she's a greater blockage of the wind.
So therefore that's how you're, so that's how you're using her, the
kid, the person is asleep and you're using the woman. But, but
the funny thing is again, if you then went ahead and just
sold the woman outright after using her that way, or sold the
sleep or the sleeping person became aware and you sold him, you
would be חייב. chayav. So it's not just that point of use,
it's that then somehow they were sold in this way also that
highlighted the fact, you know, that, so it's not, it's really about
the sale, not about the use. I don't really fully understand this.
One minute. So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, we don't know.
So I like I said, I don't really understand it, but it
seems to me what it's getting at is the point that, as
I said before, it's not just like, oh we have a checkbox,
did you use them, check. Like the point of using them, of
using is to, to create the context that this person is now
being enslaved. And I'm making this person a slave. Okay, so even
if the use of when somebody's asleep could sort of be seen
as a legitimate use, okay, but if the person isn't aware that
they're being enslaved, right, so they're completely oblivious, how much have have
I enslaved a person, meaning, you know, I've used them, but like
as soon as the person wakes up they'll protest, they'll run away,
who knows how they'll...
Well you shackled them and they didn't wake up or something like
that, you know what I mean?
You attached a load to them. Okay, but but I'm not just
saying they could escape, but the fact is is that somehow it's,
you know, you think that when you say somebody's enslaved, it's hard
to imagine a case that you would just could describe somebody as
being enslaved if they're oblivious to the fact. Okay, that the fact
is somehow that that has been imposed on the person and they're
aware of it is part of I think how we imagine what
it means to sort of be enslaving someone. So anyway, so that,
so that's how I understand it. Meaning the problem isn't you didn't
do a sale. Of course you did a sale, you bought somebody
and you picked them up. But how much is the sale defined
by the עימור? imur? How much is it not just that I've
used him, but then that creates a context where I've sold the
person as a slave? So if I lie on him, lay on
him I guess, when he was asleep and then he woke up
and I sold him and he was aware that he was being
sold. then you combined the pieces. I used him, right, and then
I sold him, and then he was aware he was being sold,
and I had used him, so that creates a context of selling
him as a slave. But if the whole thing is oblivious, maybe
those pieces don't combine, right? And the same with like the pregnant
woman, right? If I, you know, used her, fine, I used her,
but like how much did I, like, is am I like selling,
I don't know, I'd have to figure out the pieces. But anyway,
but it's somehow like, you know, how much is if is
selling the fetus and not selling her but selling her for the
fetus sort of like enslaving her? And that's sort of I think
part of the question. So the question isn't like is it או
מכרו, o macharo, is it a sale? Yes, it's a sale, but
the דרך עמר derech imur is is it a sale of enslavement?
And that's sort of that's why it's framed as דרך עמר derech
imur because the עמר imur is what creates the context of enslavement.
That's how I'm understanding it. Yes.
I mean, we don't get to it, but you know, I was
going to have like the question I had on the פסוקים pesukim
because there's two, there's משפטים Mishpatim one which is
וגונב איש ומכרו ונמצא בידו מות יומת, vegonev ish umacharo venimtza beyado
mot yumat, right? Doesn't mention עמר, imur, right? And the other one
does. So you know, in דברים. Devarim. So the question is was
it sort of expanding it or was it separate things? Because בפרשת
משפטים b'parshat Mishpatim you can say if he's still in my possession,
you know, that's worse somehow, right? So I don't even need עמר,
imur, right? If he's not in my possession, right?
So you could have said that that was a debate of the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda because one פסוק
pasuk doesn't mention עמר. imur. The גמרא Gemara is choosing to assume
that and then maybe say you understand דברה תורה, dibra Torah, you
know, whatever, you know, just דרך derech like in a normal case
but it wasn't a technical legal requirement. But the גמרא Gemara is
not reading it that way. The גמרא Gemara understands you can't ignore
that פסוק pasuk and it's choosing to read that even the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma agrees to that criteria. But that's what I'm saying.
It seems to me that the purpose of that is to create
the context and that explains why it's in דברים Devarim and not
in שמות, Shemot, that it's a technical point that's necessary to create
the context that you are enslaving, you are you've captured the person
as a slave and you're selling him as a slave and you
know it's that context is is created through that עמר, imur, which
is how this גמרא Gemara right now that we read understands why
the עמר imur can affect the nature of the sale.
So the עמר imur doesn't so so you saying it's technical because
the person may not even be realized may not be whatever you
want to call it
slave, the נגנב, negnav,
yeah, may not even be realizing that he's like being well that's
the
that's the case of the גמרא Gemara about a sleep, right? Exactly.
All right. Oh my god like you know he realizes oh this
is terrible and
all right but he does but then he realizes when he's awake,
which is why the גמרא Gemara has a question if he's asleep
the whole time. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Anyway, like I said it's not totally spelled
out how it's connecting the dots but it seems clear that the
idea of עמר imur is to create this context of enslavement. Okay.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. כי ימצא איש גונב נפש
מאחיו, ki yimatzei ish gonev nefesh me'achiv, אין לי אלא איש ein
li ela ish שגנב, sheganav, אשה ishah okay כי ימצא ki yimatzei
if we've had the similar thing before, if a man, how do
you know it refers to a woman? אשה מנין? ishah minayin? תלמוד
לומר. talmud lomar. Now by the way תוספות Tosafot has pointed out
I should mention earlier, it's a funny thing because often the גמרא
Gemara says that you know כל התורה כולה בלשון זכר נאמר, kol
hatorah kullah bilshon zachar ne'emar, right? Which is like the entire תורה
Torah always sort of you know is in the male pronoun like
if a man does this, a man does that and so on,
right? And nevertheless the גמרא Gemara says like הוקשה אשה לאיש, huksha
ishah l'ish, you know, איש לאשה ish l'ishah כל עונשים שבתורה. kol
onshim shebaTorah. We assume, right, unless it's something specifically male like talking
about you know an act of intercourse with a woman or whatever,
you know we assume that every prohibition applies equally to a man
and a woman. Okay. So תוספות Tosafot says why do we sometimes
need a special way to include women, right, if you know we
should just by default assume that even if it's written in the
male it includes women? All right. So תוספות Tosafot raises that question,
you know, in various places he gives different types of answers but
I just did sort of want to put it out there. You
know somebody actually told me that there was a woman lawyer a
couple years back in Israel of course who was also sort of
annoyed by the fact that all of Israeli legislation was in the
masculine, right? If a person, if he, if whatever. And anyway found
somewhere that there was some law somewhere that said that any you
know any legislation that's written in either gender should be assumed to
apply to the other gender unless stated explicitly otherwise. So then she
started working to pass you know as much leg you know as
much legislation as possible on the female gender, right? But I should
say that somebody recently gave me that feedback because we're dealing with
all these people that are חייב מיתה, chayav misa, right? Somebody who
hits a mother or father, somebody who curses a mother father, somebody
who worships עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and I tend to use the
male gender, you know, if he, like often I'm good to use
balance but it was like you know it's like that whole question
about you know nope if women if equal treatment for women they
could be doing the עבירות aveiras as well as the men I
should have just assumed that the men are doing the עבירות, aveiras,
right? So okay so everybody so I plea guilty on all of
that. Anyway all right. What?
That's not helpful actually. First do all the good stuff. Well that's
the whole question about the draft, right? About the whole affirmative action
and what about where you know oh so does that mean that
women should be drafted as well? So okay right we could have
that discussion. I don't have an opinion on that. We could have
that discussion.
Oh that's what I think. Only if you make them into the
generals not if you make them into the foot soldiers.
Yes we do interchange the one female and male he and her.
Oh,
yeah, yeah, no, in general I'm good about it, but I've been
like reluctant to do it with all of these capital crimes here.
Okay, anyway, כי ימצא איש גנב נפש מאחיו מבני ישראל והתעמר בו
ומכרו ומת הגנב ההוא ובערת הרע מקרבך. Ki yimtza ish gonev nefesh
me'achav mibnei Yisrael vehit'amer bo umcharo umet haganav hahu uvi'arta hara mikirbecha.
אין לי אלא איש, איש שגנב. אשה מנין? Ain li ella ish,
ish sheganav. Isha minayin? For a woman is also the one who
steals, kidnaps and whatever? תלמוד לומר וגנב איש. Talmud lomar vegonev ish.
Okay, and one who steals, and it doesn't mention if a man
steals. אין לי אלא איש שגנב
בין אשה ובין איש. Ain li ella ish sheganav ben isha uven
ish. Okay, right, this is the problem that we've had before, right?
It says, it's ממש mammash it's almost the exact same like we
have have by like מקלל mekallel and other types of things. Oh
god, it says, by one פסוק pasuk says
וגנב איש, vegonev ish, so if anybody steals, but only if a
man is the one being stolen. And the one says איש ish
what it says, כי ימצא איש גנב נפש. ki yimtza ish gonev
nefesh. Okay, so here we have, we have if anybody steals a
man or if a man steals anyone, but how do you know
if anyone steals anyone? If a woman steals like steals a woman
or a woman steals a baby or something like that? Okay, right?
And נפש nefesh here would mean even a female and even a
baby, right? And the וגנב vegonev here means even a female, not
a baby because you have to be an adult. Okay, but how
do you know if a woman steals a woman or a woman
steals a baby or whatever? How would you include that? Okay. אין
לי
אלא איש שגנב בין אשה ובין איש. ואשה שגנבה איש, אשה שגנבה
אשה מנין? Ain li ella ish sheganav ben isha uven ish. Ve'isha
sheganava ish, isha sheganava isha minayin? And a woman stealing a woman,
תלמוד לומר ומת הגנב ההוא, Talmud lomar umet haganav hahu, מכל מקום.
mikol makom. Okay, so the הגנב, haganav, whatever the circumstances is of
the גניבה, gneiva,
בין אשה ובין
איש.
ben isha
uven ish.
Right, I understand. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we've done another ברייתא, beraisa,
כי ימצא איש גנב נפש מאחיו. Ki yimtza ish gonev nefesh me'achav.
אחד הגונב את האיש ואחד הגונב את האשה Echad hagonev es ha'ish
ve'echad hagonev es ha'isha because it says נפש, nefesh, whether you're stealing
a man or a woman, ואחד גר ואחד עבד משוחרר וקטן חייב,
ve'echad ger ve'echad eved meshuchrar vekatan chayav, and whether the person stolen
is a, like you might say what is מאחיו, me'achav, from the
brethren, so who might that be excluding? So it does not exclude
a גר, ger, a convert, that's included in אחד, echad, and it
doesn't include a free slave who's like a convert who's included in
אחד echad now as part of the brethren, and a minor also
whether it being the stolen person. All of those is חייב. chayav.
Now, גנבה, ganva, but of course somebody who's currently a slave would
not be included. Now that could be partly because, now is that
because somebody who's currently a slave is excluded from מאחיו, me'achav, or
is that because somebody who's a slave, it's part of the whole
sin is enslaving a free person? Okay, so we'll see in the
גמרא Gemara how we know to exclude a slave. Now, גנבה ולא
מכרה, מכרה ועדיין ישנו ברשותו. ganva velo machra, machra va'adayin yeshno birshuso.
If he stolen and he was not sold or sold and he
still is in his domain. Now whose is the his domain? It
sounds like I went ahead and I stole a kid and he's
still in my yard and I sold him to Michael and Michael
didn't take him out of my yard. And you could imagine that,
right? What does it mean to steal, to sell? Right, because it's
not a legally binding sale, so you say that the requirements are
sale means that Michael has now taken him out of my yard
and taken him off this plantation, right, and then you understand like
now he's not going to get back to his parents or whatever
the case might be. But basically רש"י Rashi reads עדיין היא ברשותו
adayin hi birshuso and the רמב"ם Rambam reads it as well, meaning
he's still in the, he's still in the kid's original רשות. reshus.
Like I never really took him home, okay? I picked him up,
I transacted a sale with Michael, I found him in the middle
of the street, okay, but I never took him home, which is
going back to the point of our משנה mishna that I'm not
חייב chayav until I bring him into my into my control. We'll
get to it. Okay, פטור, patur, in all those cases you're exempt.
All right, but again I do wonder if there are ראשונים rishonim
who read it the other way, that even if he is in
the גנב's ganav רשות reshus but has not yet gone into the
purchaser's רשות, reshus, is that a basis of exemption? Anyway, מכרה לאביו
או לאחיו או לאחד מן הקרובים. machra le'aviv o le'achav o le'echad
min hakrovim. You sold him back to the family, okay, and now
the family is going to enslave him. חייב, chayav, you're חייב. chayav.
We're going to unpack all of this. הגונב את העבדים פטור, Hagonev
es ha'avadim patur, but if you steal a slave you're exempt. Okay,
the top of פ"ו עמוד א'. peh-vov amud aleph. תני תנא קמיה
דרב ששת. Tani tanna kamei d'Rav Sheshes. So the תנא tanna taught
in front of רב ששת. Rav Sheshes. אמר ליה, Amar leh, אני
שונה ani shoneh רבי שמעון אומר מאחיו עד שיוציאנו מרשות אחיו Rabbi
Shimon omer me'achav ad sheyotzi'ennu mereshus achav ואת אמרת חייב? פטור. ve'at
amrat chayav? Patur. So he taught this ברייתא beraisa that we just
taught that said that if you sell to the father you're חייב
chayav and he said, how could you say that? I have the
tradition that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that it says גנב נפש
מאחיו gonev nefesh me'achav
that you have to take him away from the family. So if
you sold him back to the family, that's not taking him מאחיו,
me'achav, you're not taking him away from the family. So I would
say he's exempt. How can you say he's חייב? chayav?
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, okay,
so the גמרא Gemara we're going to see that in a minute.
So you should change your גירסא. girsa. No, if you sold him
back to the family you're פטור. patur. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאי קשיא, mai kashya, why is that a problem? דילמא הא רבי
שמעון הא רבנן, Dilma ha Rabbi Shimon ha Rabbanan, that's רבי שמעון's
Rabbi Shimon position that if you sell back to the family you're
פטור. patur. Maybe he was telling you the position of the תנא
tanna of of a different rabbi? So he says no, לא סלקא
דעתך. lo salka datach. Doesn't make sense that that ברייתא braita was
a different position than רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. Why? דאמר רבי יוחנן
d'amar Rabbi Yochanan סתם מתניתין רבי מאיר, stam matnitin Rebbi Meir, the
anonymous משנה Mishnah is רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, סתם תוספתא רבי נחמיה,
stam Tosefta Rebbi Nechemya, an anonymous תוספתא Tosefta is רבי נחמיה, Rebbi
Nechemya, סתם ספרא רבי יהודה, stam Sifra Rebbi Yehuda, the anonymous ספרא
Sifra which is the Tannaitic commentary on ויקרא Vayikra is רבי יהודה,
Rebbi Yehuda, סתם ספרי stam Sifrei which is the Rabbinic Tannaitic commentary
on במדבר Bamidbar and דברים Devarim is רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, and
this is a ספרי Sifrei because this was an explication of the
verse in דברים. Devarim. Okay, וכולהו אליבא דרבי עקיבא, vechulo aliba d'Rebbi
Akiva, and they're all from the school of
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva because these are all students of רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva as opposed to the
רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael Tannaitic
מדרשי הלכה. midreshei halacha. So since you're teaching me a ספרי Sifrei
which is רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, I believe that there could be
another opinion that says חייב, chayav, but I believe that a ספרי
Sifrei would say פטור. patur. That's my understanding of רבי שמעון's Rebbi
Shimon position. Okay, הגונב בנו. hagonev beno. Now back to our case
of the משנה, Mishnah, somebody who steals his own son, which is
similar to stealing somebody and selling it back to a parent. Here
it is somebody who steals his own son. Okay, so that's the
debate: the rabbis say you're פטור patur and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says you're חייב—sorry, chayav רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, yeah, בנו של יוחנן
בן ברוקא bno shel Yochanan ben Beroka says you're חייב chayav and
the rabbis say you're פטור. patur. מאי טעמא דרבנן? mai ta'ama d'rabanan?
What's the reason of the רבנן? rabanan? אביי Abaye says קרא, kara,
the verse says
כי ימצא, ki yimatzei, פרט למצוי prat l'matzuy
to exclude a case where it's not just you discover a person
doing this, but it's also read as if the person finds somebody
to steal as opposed to somebody who's always available.
But איש ish is the person stealing, not the person being stolen.
I understand, that's why I just said that the גמרא Gemara is
reading this not like פשט. peshat. Okay, כי ימצא ki yimatzei is
not just that the stealer is discovered, but the one being stolen
is discovered as opposed to if the one being stolen is already
present. By the way, the most common application of this type of
a דרשה derasha is by the מצוה mitzvah of שילוח הקן, shiluach
haken, that if somebody is, or קן kan I should say, somebody
basically is raising chickens and goes ahead and let's say takes a
chicken to slaughter it and do they have to do the מצוה
mitzvah of שילוח shiluach or takes the eggs, why don't they have
to send away the chicken? They're raising eggs, right? So it says
כי יקרא, ki yikarei, right,
it says what's the whole פסוק, pasuk, קן צפור לפניך בדרך kan
tzipor lefanecha baderech etc., so כי יקרא, ki yikarei, פרט למצוי, prat
l'matzuy, if you're raising them, it doesn't apply. Okay, anyway, so here
it's although here it's כי ימצא ki yimatzei that the גנב ganav
is discovered, but we're reading it that the נגנב nignav is discovered.
Does this mean it's a minor child who's more likely to be
found by his father as opposed to an adult child who's on
his own?
Interesting, that's an interesting question, maybe.
Because since they're children, they may be coming home?
Yeah, I don't know, it's a good question what the parameters of
that are. Okay, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, אביי Abaye says קרא, kara,
כי ימצא, ki yimatzei, פרט למצוי. prat l'matzuy. אמר ליה רב פפא
לאביי, amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, כי ימצא
איש שוכב עם אשה בעולת בעל, ki yimatzei ish shochev im isha
be'ulat ba'al, if a man is discovered sleeping with a married woman,
הכא נמי, hacha nami, כי ימצא, ki yimatzei, פרט למצוי? prat l'matzuy?
So if they're living in close quarters with one couple with another
couple, so כגון שבית פלוני, kegon shebeit ploni, like those guys over
there, that household,
דשכיחי גבייהו, dishchichin gabeihu, that maybe that they have a lot, that
the married couples are like living in close proximity, maybe under the
same roof, so הכא נמי דפטירי? hacha nami d'ptiri? Would you say
they're exempt?
אמר ליה, amar lei, אנא ומנמצא בידו קאמינא. ana mivenimtza beyado ka'amina.
So this also gets the problem that the כי ימצא ki yimatzei
is going on the perpetrator. So I'm not dealing with that. That's—you're
right, then it would apply—you could ask the same question by this
case of adultery. I'm talking about כי ימצא איש גונב נפש מאחיו
מבני ישראל והתעמר בו ומכרו. ki yimatzei ish gonev nefesh me'echav mibnei
Yisrael vehitamer bo umacharo. No, that's this פסוק, pasuk, right? This is
the פסוק pasuk of ונמצא בידו, venimtza beyado, right? גונב איש ומכרו
ונמצא בידו מות יומת. gonev ish umacharo venimtza beyado mot yumot. So
obviously the problem of ונמצא בידו venimtza beyado is that he's not
discovered in the hand of the גנב. ganav. If he was sold
off, he's discovered in the hand of the buyer. So ונמצא בידו
venimtza beyado means somehow we read it like, okay, the עדים eidim
saw the גנב ganav in the act of the perpetration of the
crime. Okay, but here ונמצא בידו venimtza beyado is also meant like
that all of a sudden the person became the נגנב, nignav, became
now found in the גנב's ganav hand. He wasn't normally under the
control of the גנב. ganav. Which is like a good פשט peshat
in the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk is like: what is this
guy doing in your house? He shouldn't be here. He was discovered
in the house and he didn't belong in the house. But if
he belonged in the house, then the גנב ganav would be exempt.
What they're saying is גונב איש ומכרו ונמצא בידו. gonev ish umacharo
venimtza beyado.
It's not saying
the נגנב nignav is נמצא בידו nimtza beyado of the גנב, ganav,
which means that like he was now discovered in this guy's house
and he shouldn't have been in this guy's house, right?
Meaning it
doesn't—that's not the timing of the sale, right? Meaning it could be—you
could have sold him and he's no longer in his house.
That's what I said, right? That's the fun part of the פסוק
pasuk is that the פסוק pasuk sound like you have to catch
him while he's still in the גנב's ganav house. But like what
it really means is that
the עדים eidim have to witness the transaction, so they are seeing
that the guy is still in... in the house as it were.
Okay, but your whatever. Although it's an interesting question, right? Do the
עדים edim have to see, like let's say עדים edim see ראובן
Reuven steal this kid? And then a week later they say ראובן
Reuven engaged in a transaction with שמעון Shimon to sell the kid,
but they don't know where the kid is right now. You know,
like where, how do you satisfy that ונמצא בידו? venimtza biyado? But
anyway here it's being read that it implies that the kid did—I'm
always giving an example of a kid because it's an easier scenario
to imagine but obviously it would apply to adults as well—but anyway
that the נגנב nignav did not belong in the household of the
person who where he was where he was being taken and sold
from. Okay, let's just read it, hold on. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara is going to actually get that. You're very good, you're anticipating
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so it says קאמינא. Kamina. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, here אנא לה מונמצא בידו קאמינא. Anale minnimtza biyado kamina. אמר
רבא הלכך הני מקרי דרדקי ומשני רבנן, Amar Rava hilchach hani mikrei
dardeki umasnei rabanan, so those people that teach school kids and that
or they teach like you know more like the that so מקרי
דרדקי mikrei dardeki is teaching תורה Torah like written תורה Torah to
the kids, and משני רבנן masnei rabanan is teaching like משנה Mishnah
to the older kids, so what is it like lower school and
high school teachers כמצויים בידם דמי. kimtzuim biyadan dami. If they kidnap
one of their charges so then they're exempt and פטור, patur, they're
exempt which is ironic because you would think that those are the
people you need more the laws to. Are the strangers whom you
know they're under the control of strangers right and they're entrusted and
these people have you know have these positions of trust is דוקא
davka where you would think you would need to have you know
more of the safeguards.
It's not that the נגנב nignav is in the house of the
גנב gannav often, it's just that the גנב gannav is readily available.
Right. Which also by the way raises an interesting question about brothers
right? You think about יוסף Yosef and the brothers right? Like we
said אלה אזכרה eileh ezkera right? נמצא בידו Nimtza biyado whatever גונב
איש ומכרו, gonev ish umachro, like how come if a brother steals
another brother they should be פטור, patur, right? It's נמצא בידו, nimtza
biyado, right? Is it is it not just that you're around them
but they're under your control maybe it has to do right that
ונמצא venimtza so maybe it דוקא davka would not apply to like
brothers you know at the same house. And they would be exempt?
Right, that's my point. So maybe it also has to be that
they're under the control. Okay, anyway so let's take a look. גמרא
Gemara says like this: גונב מחצי עבד. gonev mi-chatzi eved. Now stealing
somebody who's half slave, what's that about? What's the debate about? So
תנן התם, tenan hatam, we taught over there. רבי יהודה אומר אין
לעבדים בושת. Rabbi Yehuda omer ein la-avadim boshet.
So we're going to see why this is relevant because here רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that if you steal somebody who's a half
slave you're חייב. chayav. Okay, which seems to be that he's more
sort of recognizing if you would the humanity or the free nature
of a half slave. So but don't go thinking that רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda this big protector of slaves because here it's going to
seem like this other debate it's going to be the reverse. Okay,
so אין לעבדים בושת ein la-avadim boshet that if you embarrass a
slave do you have to pay damages? So he said no, there's
no damage payments to a slave. Now read it one way it
means like he doesn't believe that slaves could be embarrassed. They're already
in this degraded type of a state. They don't become embarrassed but
that's not how we read it. We read it as they're not
entitled to the payment to such a payment. Why not? So let's
take a look. מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה, mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda, what's
the reason? נאמר קרא, ne'emar kra, the verse says כי ינצו אנשים
יחדו איש ואחיו, ki yinatzu anashim yachdav ish ve-achiv, if two
brothers fight or a man and his brother—not literally brothers anyway—and then
it says it speaks about a woman, one of the wives you
know tries to defend her husband and you know and grabs hold
of the privates of the other person. It says you cut off
her hand. So we interpret that not to be cut literally cut
off her hand, we interpret it to mean a payment for embarrassment.
Okay, so this is the context where we learn there's a payment
for בושת. boshet. And it starts by brothers fight. Again brothers meant
more figuratively than literal but anyway. So מי שיש לו אחוה, mi
she-yesh lo achva, so the payments of בושת boshet applies only to
somebody who's considered to have a brotherhood. יצא עבד שאין לו אחוה,
yatza eved she-ein lo achva, slaves don't have brotherhood. Now what does
that mean? So תוספות Tosafot says what it basically means is is
that if a
slave gives like—it doesn't just mean oh you know like they're not
halachically related to their brothers because if תוספות Tosafot said if that
were true it would also apply to a convert. Somebody converts, they're
not related to their biological brothers from the past. But what it
means is no, somebody who converts their kids are all considered to
be you know brothers and sisters right? Once they've converted their children
are all part of the same family. Whereas a slave as a
slave even his children are not considered to be part of his
family. Okay, so this whole family structure doesn't apply halachically by slaves.
Obviously that also reflects a reality that families were broken up right?
So the law didn't recognize the family structure by slaves. Okay, so
יצא עבד שאין לו אחוה, yatza eved she-ein lo achva,
so therefore a slave is excluded there's no בושת. boshet. רבנן Rabanan
and the rabbis say אחיו הוא במצוות. achiv hu be-mitzvot.
No, אחיו הוא במצוות. achiv hu be-mitzvot. No no no he still
is your brother in the world of מצוות mitzvot not from a
from a sort of biological family structure
but because a slave is obligated in מצוות mitzvot he still part
of he's one of us right? He's within the sort of Jewish
faith and the Jewish community. Okay, so that's the debate of whether
slaves have בושת. boshet. Now what's the debate here where they seem
to flip? positions, that a half-slave רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says you're
חייב Chayav *chayav* and the חכמים *Chachamim* say you're פטור *patur*. והכא
היכי דרש רבי יהודה *Vehacha heichi darsh Rabbi Yehuda*, how does רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* interpret the פסוקים *pesukim* here? סבר *Savar*, מאחיו *me'achav*,
it says כי ימצא איש גנב נפש מאחיו מבני ישראל *ki yimatze
ish gonev nefesh me'achav mibnei Yisrael*, stealing one's brothers from the children
of Israel. Okay, מאחיו *me'achav*, לאפוקי עבדים *l'afukei avadim*, so that would
exclude slaves because we know רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* excludes slaves from
the word brother. בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael*, then it says children of
Israel, למיעוטי *limutei*, so that's now even being more exclusionary. למיעוטי *limutei*,
that would exclude מי שחצי עבד וחצי בן חורין *mi shechetzi eved
v'chetzi ben chorin*, even a half-slave you're exempt from. But then there's
another word to exclude: מבני ישראל *Mi-Bnei Yisrael*, the mem means even
a small subset of that. Okay, מבני ישראל *Mi-Bnei Yisrael*, so למיעוטי
*limutei*, so that's also excluding מי שחצי עבד וחצי בן חורין *mi
shechetzi eved v'chetzi ben chorin*, a half-slave. But we already excluded that.
So this is the classic, you know, like bizarre reverse logic of
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. הוי מיעוט אחר מיעוט *Havei mi'ut achar mi'ut*,
this is the principle of methinks she doth protest too much. It's
excluding after something's already been excluded, ואין מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות
*v'ein mi'ut achar mi'ut ela l'rabos*. So if you're so insistent that
it's excluded, it really is included. Okay, so because he starts by
excluding slaves more, he winds up having excluded them too much and
therefore winds up including somebody who's a half-slave into this prohibition. That's
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. ורבנן *V'rabanan*, and the Rabbis, because they start
with less exclusion, they wind up with more. מאחיו לאפוקי עבדים לא
משמע להו *Me'achav l'afukei avadim lo mashma lehu*, they don't think אחיו
*achiv* excludes slaves, דהא אחיו במצוות *deha achiv b'mitzvos*. So בני ישראל
*Bnei Yisrael*, only the word בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* begins to exclude
slaves. בני ישראל מבני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael, Mi-Bnei Yisrael*, so now we
have two exclusions: בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael*, right, and which would exclude
slaves, and מבני ישראל *Mi-Bnei Yisrael*, the extra mem. So חד למיעוטי
עבד וחד למיעוטי מי שחצי עבד וחצי בן חורין *chad l'mutei eved
v'chad l'mutei mi shechetzi eved v'chetzi ben chorin*, one excludes a full
slave and the other to exclude a half-slave. So that's why they
wound up to some degree reversing their positions of how excluded a
slave is by בושת *boshes* to how excluded a half-slave is here
by the case of kidnapping. Okay, now, now we move on. אזהרה
לגונב נפש מניין *Azhara l'gonev nefesh minayin*, where's the prohibition of kidnapping?
רבי יאשיה אומר *Rabbi Yoshiya omer*, מלא תגנב *mi-lo tignov*, from the
Ten Commandments, thou shalt not steal. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan אומר *Rabbi
Yochanan omer*, מלא ימכרו ממכרת עבד *mi-lo yimachru mimcheras aved*. Do not
they shall not be sold, right? This is talking about how you
treat when you're you
know
when a fellow Jew sells himself as a slave, how you have
to treat him. And it says, you know, כי עבדי הם אשר
הוצאתי אתם מארץ מצרים *ki avadai heim asher hotzeisi osam me'eretz Mitzrayim*,
they're My slaves, לא ימכרו ממכרת עבד *lo yimachru mimcheras aved*, they
shall not be sold like a slave is sold. Okay, so that
means according to this, it's not just like a declaration, that's saying
don't sell a free Jew as a slave. All right, so ולא
פליגי *v'lo pligi*, and they're really not debating. מר קחשיב לאו דגניבה
ומר קחשיב לאו דמכירה *Mar kachashiv lav d'geneiva u-mar kachashiv lav d'mechira*,
there's two prohibitions. There's a prohibition of stealing and a prohibition of
selling. A person only gets מיתה misah. *misa* if they do both,
but each act is independently prohibited. Okay, so one wonders actually, let's
say somebody never sold somebody, right? Let's say he stole somebody. Let's
say I go to Jen and I say, Jen, you see that
kid walking down over there? He's my slave. I'll sell him to
you. And we transact and I never even touched the kid. Okay,
and then Jen sends her you know her troops or her men
or whatever, they pick up the kid and they take him off
to Jen's plantation. Okay, so have I done so Jen was unwitting,
all right, I didn't steal him, have I done the transgression of
לא ימכרו ממכרת עבד *lo yimachru mimcheras aved*? Is it possible to
do that transgression without I'm not gonna get מיתה *misa* because I
haven't stolen him. You need to do both to get מיתה *misa*,
but is it possible to do the second transgression without having done
the first? I don't know. Okay, anyway, moving on.
The whole thing's a false sale. Even if I stole him, it's
a false sale. He's a free person, right? The whole thing is
just looks like a sale, but it's not, right? Let's say I
have your kid over at my house for a you know to
be raking the lawn. And then I go to Jen and I
say, you see that kid raking the lawn? He's my slave. I'll
sell him to you. I didn't steal him, right? But even if
I did steal him, I'm not selling him. He's not really mine,
he's not a slave. All right, so okay, so תנו רבנן *tano
rabanan*, לא תגנב Lo Tignov, *lo tignov*, בגונב נפשות הכתוב מדבר *b'gonev
nefashos hakatuv medaber*. Now we're getting back to the idea that the
Ten Commandments, לא תגנב *lo tignov*, is talking about kidnapping. So most
people of course you know you know like have no idea that
this is how the Rabbis read it. If you read רש"י *Rashi*
on the on the פסוקים *pesukim*, you know that רש"י *Rashi* quotes
this. Right, but anyway, but he says that's kidnapping. So לא תגנב
*lo tignov*, בגונב נפשות הכתוב מדבר *b'gonev nefashos hakatuv medaber*. אתה אומר
בגונב נפשות או אינו אלא בגונב ממון *Atah omer b'gonev nefashos o
eino ela b'gonev mamon*, maybe it's talking about stealing property. property. אמרת,
צא ולמד משלוש עשרה מדות שהתורה נדרשת בהם. Amarta tze ulemad mishlosh
esrei middos shehatorah nidreshet bahem. Go and learn from the thirteen principles
that the Torah is derived from, right, that we say דרבי ישמעאל
De'Rabbi Yishmael at the end of the קרבנות. korbanos. What's one of
them? דבר הלמד מענינו. Davar halamed me'inyano. Learning something from context. That's
a simple principle. Let's just figure out what it means from context.
במה הכתוב מדבר בנפשות. Beme hakatuv medaber binefashos. The whole context there,
right, is about לא תרצח, Lo Tirtzach, לא תנאף, Lo Tin'af, לא
תגנב, so the whole context is about
capital crime. So since it's about capital crimes, we'll assume this is
also capital crimes. Of course, of course, afterwards it gets into non-capital
crimes, right? לא תענה ברעך עד שקר, Lo ta'aneh berayacha ed shaker,
לא תחמד בית רעך. Lo tachmod beit rayacha. So good, before it
was capital, but afterwards it's not capital crimes. But somehow we're saying
that because preceding it was capital crimes, this has to be a
type of stealing that's a capital crime and therefore it has to
be this kidnapping. Okay, so,
so, אף כאן בנפשות. af kan binefashos. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we
learned in another ברייתא, Braisa, לא תגנבו, Lo Tignovu, this is in
ויקרא, Vayikra, לא תגנבו Lo Tignovu in the plural. בגונב ממון הכתוב
מדבר. Begonev mamon hakatuv medaber. That's talking about stealing property. אתה אומר
בגונב ממון או אינו אלא בגונב נפשות? Atah omer begonev mamon o
eino ela begonev nefashos? Maybe that's about stealing people. אמרת צא ולמד
משלוש עשרה מדות שהתורה נדרשת בהם. tze ulemad mishlosh esrei middos shehatorah
nidreshet bahem. No, learn from the thirteen principles. דבר הלמד מענינו. Davar
halamed me'inyano. One of them is context. במה הכתוב מדבר בממון. Beme
hakatuv medaber bemamon.
That פסוק pasuk is לא תכחשו, lo techachashu, what is it? לא
תשקרו ולא תכחשו, lo tishakru velo techachashu,
לא תגנבו ולא תכחשו ולא תשקרו איש בעמיתו. Lo Tignovu velo techachashu
velo tishakru ish ba'amito. Don't steal, don't lie, don't deny that you
owe something. So the whole context there is about stealing and monetary
issues, not about taking some, not about capital crimes.
Okay, בממון אף כאן בממון. bemamon af kan bemamon. Fine, so that's
the end of the basis for it. Now we get to a
different question, which is combining, since there are these two principal points,
stealing and selling, how does it work in terms of the testifying
that the person has done both? So I do want to say
the next גמרא Gemara is a little bizarre because
it
focuses on whether people are falsely testifying, under what circumstances can they
become עדים זוממים? edim zomemim? But really the prior question is, if
they're telling the truth, when can they combine, when is it considered
to be that each one is giving a sufficient testimony on their
own to combine to make the person liable for having done this
sin? But for whatever reason we're focusing on if they're lying can
they become עדים זוממים? edim zomemim? But it really parallels the question
of when can two testimonies combine to make somebody liable for this
capital crime? Okay, so let's take a look.
איתמר, Itmar, it was said, עדי גניבה ועדי מכירה. eidei gneiva ve'eidei
mechira. So witnesses say that ראובן Reuven stole this person, and then
other witnesses say that he sold it. בנפש שהוזמו. Benefesh shehuzmu. And
they were proven עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. So חזקיה אומר אין נהרגים.
Chizkiya omer ein neheragim. You can't kill them because רבי יוחנן אומר
נהרגים, Rabbi Yochanan omer neheragim, you can't kill them... you can kill
them. So why can't you kill them? They were trying to get
the guy killed. So חזקיה אומר כרבי עקיבא דאמר דבר ולא חצי
דבר. Chizkiya omer ke'Rabbi Akiva de'amar davar velo chatzi davar. It has
to be a full thing, not a half thing. רבי יוחנן אומר
כרבנן דאמרי דבר ואפילו חצי דבר, Rabbi Yochanan omer ke'rabbanan de'amri davar
ve'afillu chatzi davar, even half. So what does that mean? Okay, so
here they are.
Here's this guy
who they are saying, okay, so these witnesses say
we
saw him steal the kid. Okay, I guess he'll have him holding
up a little kid that he stole. Okay, and then these witnesses
say,
I
don't know why I'm going up to be, anyway, but that we
saw him sell the kid. All right,
yeah, he's handing over the kid to this other person.
Okay, you like my pictograms? Okay,
good point, okay, good point.
Okay, fine. All right, so, all right, so before you get to
עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, like I said, it's strange the גמרא Gemara
starts with עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. Do the same witnesses have to
see both? Because there's a principle, על פי שנים עדים יקום דבר,
al pi shnayim edim yakum davar, דבר ולא חצי דבר, davar velo
chatzi davar, at least if you make that דרשה. drasha. You have
to testify to something that in itself is a whole thing. So
the point is, well, if they just saw that he stole or
they just saw that he sold, first of all, he could have
been selling somebody who actually was his slave, but neither of them
alone is testifying to a whole thing because neither of them alone
says is there significance to their testimony? The testimony only means something
when you combine it. So חזקיה Chizkiya who says that if they're
זוממים zomemim they're not נהרגים, neheragim, what he really is saying before
you get to whether they're זוממים zomemim is that they can't kill
him. The reason they're not נהרגים neheragim if they're זוממים zomemim is
because their testimony won't get this guy killed, because the testimony won't
combine, because each testimony doesn't stand on its own. Okay, so that's
חזקיה'ס Chizkiya's point. So let's read that. חזקיה דאמר כרבי עקיבא דאמר
דבר ולא חצי דבר. Chizkiya de'amar ke'Rabbi Akiva de'amar davar velo chatzi
davar. You can't testify to a half thing. So
therefore if they're lying they also won't get killed. And (רבי יוחנן)
Rabbi Yochanan. (אמר כרבנן דאמר דאפילו חצי דבר). amar k'Rabbanan d'amar d'afillu
chatzi davar No, you can testify to a half thing. This is
accepted, this is accepted, we the court combine the testimony and we
would get the guy killed. And since we would get the guy
killed by these two testimonies, if they're lying, we'll kill them. Okay?
So that's the debate. So now the (גמרא) Gemara says like this:
(ומודה חזקיה בעדים האחרונים של בן סורר ומורה שהוזמו שנהרגים מתוך שיכולים
לומר הראשונים להלקותו באנו). u'modeh Chizkiyah b'eidim ha-achronim shel ben sorer u'moreh
she-huz-mu she-neheragim mitokh she-yekholim lomar ha-rishonim le-halkoso banu Okay, so what happens
if I have a (בן סורר ומורה)? ben sorer u'moreh Let's say
it's not this case, let's say it's another case, here we'll draw
it here. So here, they basically, these witnesses say right here is
the kid is going ahead and he's misbehaving and the parents are
telling him we don't want to see you doing this again, right?
That's (ויסרו אותו), v'yisru oto right? And then he goes ahead and
he goes ahead and he steals, okay, after he was warned by
his parents. He steals some money and he eats something, he eats
the meat, whatever he's eating, okay? And they saw that and they
say "We saw him go ahead and steal the money and eat
the meat after he was warned by his parents." So the (הלכה)
halacha is (ויסרו אותו). v'yisru oto
Okay? He gets lashes. Okay? If they basically saw that. Okay? Then
he goes ahead and does it again, okay? And then he repeats
it, does it a second time, okay? And then it's (לא ישמע
אליהם), lo yishma aleihem okay? And he goes ahead and he disobeys
again and then they see it and then he gets stoned. Okay,
here that'll my stone. Okay, I guess that'll be my lashes. Okay.
Anyway, all right, so so in this case, even though we require
a full (דבר), davar you can't say a partial thing, here (חזקיה)
Chizkiyah would say these two testimonies do combine because this testimony is
sufficient in itself for a court-imposed punishment of lashes. And once this
was accepted, then when they come along, they're building on what was
already an accepted testimony in court and they're going to get him
killed. So if the first one was was accepted and had some
meaning, even though it didn't it wasn't enough to get him killed,
you can build on it for the second one. So this case
(חזקיה) Chizkiyah agrees to. But in this case, their testimony had no
meaning by itself, so therefore it doesn't combine. Yes?
Just as the first witnesses in the in the lashes case... Yes?...
become (עדים זוממים), edim zomemim
they're not going to be...
Ah, so that's the question. If they're proven (עדים זוממים), edim zomemim
you would think you should only be (מחייב) mechayev the last people,
not the early people. And we're going to say that in the
end. We haven't gotten to that, but we're going to say that
in the end.
Isn't it a similar issue over there, right?
Right. If you say these combine and they become (עדים זוממים), edim
zomemim who gets killed? You know, everybody or just these guys? So
right, it doesn't seem fair that these guys should do it unless
you can somehow prove that they were all in collusion and you
treat them as one big group. So we're going to get to
exactly that question. Okay? So the (גמרא) Gemara says: since they can
say
(להלקותו באנו), le-halkoso banu (והני אחריני כולי מילתא קעבדי), v'hani achrini kulei
milta ka-avdi and then these guys are doing something also by themselves,
they're getting him lashes and they're getting him killed. Okay. So now
the (גמרא) Gemara says like this: (מתקיף לה רב פפא): matkif lah
Rav Pappa (אי הכי), ee hachi even (עדי מכירה נמי ליקטלו), eidim
mechira nami liktilu (מתוך שיכולים עדי גניבה לומר להלקותו באנו). mitokh she-yekholim
eidim gneiva lomar le-halkoso banu Wait! But then here too (חזקיה) Chizkiyah
should agree because by saying that he stole him, right? Remember we
said that this guy's transgressing, he's transgressing the prohibition of (לא תגנוב).
lo tignov So why and what and what do you get when
you transgress a prohibition? You get lashes. So why don't we say
these guys get him lashes and these guys build on it and
get him killed? Okay? Should be the same thing.
Okay. (וכי תימא דקסבר חזקיה דלא לקי)... v'chi teima dik-savar Chizkiyah d'lo
laki but maybe (חזקיה) Chizkiyah would say that you don't get lashes
when you do this. Why would you not get lashes? Okay. So
the reason you wouldn't get lashes is because since this is a
sin that could bring about when part two is done, it gets
the guy killed, right? Because at the end of the day conceptually,
right? It's always an interesting question when there are two parts, what
do we think is the real (עבירה)? aveira Right? Like here,
would you say the (עבירה) aveira is selling somebody you stole? You
stole. We say the (עבירה) aveira is (גונב נפש מאחיו מבני ישראל).
goneiv nefesh me-echav mi-bnei Yisrael It's kidnapping. Like the sale is sort
of seen as like the end of it. So therefore when you
get- the guy will get killed over here, he's getting killed because
of the (עבירה) aveira of stealing. So that's a principle of (ניתן
להזהרת מיתת בית דין), nitan l'hazharat mitat beit din this transgression eventually
can get the guy killed. And since eventually it can get the
guy killed, he can't get lashed. lashes for it. Okay, whereas opposed
to here, right, we don't think that the reason he's getting killed
here is because of this sin, right? It's not like the later
thing is all an extension. I mean we don't know exactly why
he's getting whatever, but we know we certainly focus more on the
second act like he's a repeat offender etc. he's such a wayward
child where here we really focus on that first act. He was
a גונב נפש gonev nefesh who eventually sold it. So therefore maybe
the reason their testimony is not accepted and can't give him lashes
is because he's doing a sin that will eventually get him killed,
that could eventually get him killed. And therefore he can't get lashes.
You got it? That's called ניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין. nitan l'azharas
misas beis din. So let's read that.
So are you saying the testimony is not accepted at all?
It won't be accepted by itself because it does not have the
any effect of giving him lashes.
Okay, but let's say it's true.
Now if they say they saw him do both, it will be
accepted. Right. But if all they saw him do is this, then
that's not a testimony to give the guy lashes because even if
it's true he did it, he won't get lashes because doing a
sin that you could get you killed, well you won't be able
to give you lashes for such a sin.
So then what does that mean about the second set of witnesses?
They can't come. That could never...
Exactly. It could never work. If all according to חזקיה, Chizkiyah, the
witnesses would have to see him do both things. Okay.
Yes. And are we going to compare it to this one? Because
now I'm thinking they're pretty similar.
Well, that's what I was trying to say. This is primarily a
sin even when he sells him, it's primarily a sin of לא
תגנוב. lo tignov. It's primarily a sin of kidnapping, okay? That eventually
got sold. Here, it's not seen like this is the עבירה aveira
that gets him killed. I mean, so we're not going to make
that explicit. Well, the problem is that he's a kid
that is a wayward kid by define of having done repeat offenses,
but the primary sort of thing we're focusing on is how many
times he's been warned and whatever and now he's still doing it.
So aren't we focused on the last act? Where here we focus
on the first act as defined by provided he sells, it's conceptually
the difference, okay? Not saying it's obvious, but that's the difference, okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ובגין דמתסברא חזקיה דלא לקי.
U'vigin demis'vara Chizkiyah delo laki. Now maybe, so okay, but the גמרא
Gemara says okay, but say the same thing, get him lashes. Now
maybe you'll say oh he doesn't get lashes for the reason I
just said because eventually he's going to get killed. So the גמרא
Gemara. says one minute, you want to make that claim that according
to חזקיה Chizkiyah he doesn't get
lashes? ואיתמר, V'ismar, it was taught:
עידי גניבה בנפש שהוזמו, Eidei gneiva benefesh she'huzmu, okay, so they just
testified that he was a that he stole, again, making it an
עדים זוממים edim zomemim case, but for simplicity let's build on the
scenario of what would be if they weren't זוממים zomemim and they
actually testify. חזקיה ורבי יוחנן. Chizkiyah v'Rabbi Yochanan. It's a debate of
חזקיה Chizkiyah and רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan חד אמר לוקין וחד אמר
אין לוקין. Chad amar lokin v'chad amar ein lokin. One says you
get lashes and one says you don't. ואמינא, V'amina, and we said,
תסתיים דחזקיה דאמר לוקין. Tistayem de'Chizkiyah d'amar lokin. חזקיה Chizkiyah will say
you do get lashes. Why? דאמר חזקיה אין נהרגין. D'amar Chizkiyah ein
nehergin. Since חזקיה Chizkiyah would say that it's a little ironic but
or maybe not. Since חזקיה Chizkiyah says these two don't combine, right?
Remember חזקיה Chizkiyah says these two don't combine, right? Yes. So by
saying that they don't combine, okay, therefore it's saying that we don't
look at this as though it is this exact question of do
you look at this as all one big thing? You look at
it as two separate things, right? They were stealing and then they
were selling. For stealing you would alone you'd get lashes, for selling
after the stealing you would get whatever, you know, you'd get put
to death. Or do you look at it as one big thing?
A stealing that ends in a selling, you get put to death.
So we're going to say that according to חזקיה Chizkiyah you are
going to get lashes. How do we know you're going to get
lashes? Because if חזקיה Chizkiyah saw this, now I'm losing my own
train of thought.
If חזקיה, Chizkiyah, let's read it in again in the גמרא. Gemara
תסתיים, Tistayem, let us conclude, דחזקיה אמר לוקין, de'Chizkiyah amar lokin, you
get lashes. How do you know? דאמר חזקיה אין נהרגין. D'amar Chizkiyah
ein nehergin.
Since חזקיה Chizkiyah will say that these these two don't combine to
get him killed. Ah, that's the point. Because they don't combine to
get him killed, so this testimony
of course we're doing this the last two minutes, have to hold
cop here. But anyway, this testimony here does not this testimony
is not going to end in, right that's the point, this testimony
is not going to end in getting him killed. The only reason
not to get lashes is because as I said before, the reason
not to get lashes is because we see this as a sin
that could conclude in getting him killed. But חזקיה Chizkiyah says that
these people can never get him killed because they wouldn't combine with
the next people.
Do you sort of see that? Have I lost everybody by now?
Right, חזקיה Chizkiyah says in this scenario... scenario. Two say he stole
and two say that he sold. The guy won't get killed because
it's a half thing and they don't combine. So since it's a
half thing and it'll never combine with what comes next, it's like
a little bit circular. Since it's half and it won't combine with
what comes next, we don't have to look at this as a
capital crime because it's never going to combine, right, in this scenario.
Since it's never going to combine, we can look at it separate.
Oh, if separate, we'll give him lashes. Of course, the irony is,
well, then once you're giving him lashes, then it can combine because
then they've actually done something that was administered that was, you know,
that was meaningful in itself. It'll become a little circular. Okay, but
bracket it because that's the whole point, right? Once they give him
lashes, we can accept it and move on. But anyway, but that's
what the גמרא Gemara. is saying is, if חזקיה Chizkiyah says they
can't combine, then we don't look at this as a capital crime
and therefore we should be able to give him lashes. But once
we're giving him lashes, then we should be able to combine it.
So how do you, how do you make this make sense? Okay,
so let's read that.
תסתיים דחזקיה דאמר לוקין, Tistayeim Dechizkiyah De'amar Lokin, you get lashes. ומי
אמר חזקיה אין נהרגין, Umi Amar Chizkiyah Ein Neheragin, since they don't
get killed. די רב יוחנן כיון דאמר נהרגין, De'reb Yochanan Keivan De'amar
Neheragin, since רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan would say they would combine and
they would get him killed. היכי לקי? ניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין.
Heichi Laki? Nitan Le'azharat Mitat Beit Din.
Then it would be a transgression that would lead to the death
penalty. וכל לאו שניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין אין לוקין עליו. Vechol
Lav Shenitan Le'azharat Mitat Beit Din Ein Lokin Alav. Okay, so for
רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, they can't get him lashes because they could
combine, and once they could combine, he's on the path to getting
killed. But for חזקיה, Chizkiyah, that they can't combine and he can't
get killed, he should get lashes. But then the irony is, once
he's getting lashes, it should be able to combine, right? So like,
where do you stop?
Okay. Now, that's what he says in the, in the בן סורר
ומורה Ben Sorer Umoreh case. If they, if their testimony can be
accepted to give him lashes, then it's not a half thing, then
it's a whole thing and then the next testimony builds on it.
It's its own whole thing, but it's not, it
doesn't, yeah, but then it allows the next testimony to build on
it and get him killed.
But we said that they, that they don't build. I think it
actually makes sense, because we said that, that in this case,
that it's not a building. Are you saying the only virtue, the
only basis on which we're giving him lashes is by accepting the
idea that it can't combine with something else? So we would sort
of say both. We would say, yes, he gets lashes, but only
if you buy into the principle that we're not going any further.
Right, meaning if people come and say
I saw him sell somewhere else.
But there's nothing,
nothing to
combine it with because it only, this was only accepted on the
principle that it was going to not combine with anything else.
Point there at all, the only two witnesses who came and said
we saw him sell someone.
Right. Right, well that's certainly not the question. Can it build? So
let's see the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara, says, okay, so
therefore אילו לא לקי אינהו היכי לקי, Ilu Lo Laki Inhu Heichi
Laki, so if they can't give him lashes, they obviously won't get
lashes, which is just the point that we're talking about עדים זוממין.
Edim Zomemin. But the basic point is, according to חזקיה, Chizkiyah, he
should be able to give him lashes because since it won't build
to get him the death penalty. But once he's giving him lashes,
says the גמרא, Gemara why don't we then allow then the next
ones to come along and build on it? So Jenna has her
answer, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אלא אמר רב
פפא, Ella Amar Rav Pappa, so now רב פפא Rav Pappa is
going to make it simpler. Let's just try to get through this,
I know we're a little over, באדי מכירה דכולי עלמא לא פליגי
דנהרגין. Be'edei Mechirah Dechulei Alma Lo Peligi Deneheragin. So רב פפא Rav
Pappa says sorry Jenna, against you, that everybody will agree that these
guys can get him killed and these guys will be חייב עדים
זוממין, Chayav Edim Zomemin, whether you're dealing with בן סורר ומורה Ben
Sorer Umoreh or whether you're dealing with this. Okay, they're going to
give, this testimony is accepted because it does give him lashes. Okay,
he will get lashes. You've done a sin of לא תגנוב, Lo
Tignov, that's a sin that you know, maybe does not have to
progress on, can conceptually be seen as distinct as what you're חייב
מיתה Chayav Mitah for, the same way this is seen as distinct,
that stands by itself. Okay, we're going to give you lashes, and
therefore our testimony is accepted and therefore the next people will be
able to come along and build on it and get you killed.
Okay, so everybody agrees that that's the structure, that they can get
him killed with these two sets of witnesses. באדי מכירה דכולי עלמא
לא פליגי דנהרגין. Be'edei Mechirah Dechulei Alma Lo Peligi Deneheragin. And therefore,
if those witnesses that say he sold are עדים זוממין, Edim Zomemin,
they'll also be killed. Okay, yes, you can build on it in
two stages. כי פליגי, Ki Peligi, what's the debate? באדי גניבה, Be'edei
Geneivah, what you were saying Jenna. So it's not like we said
at all before. Everybody agrees, first set of witnesses is accepted, second
set, where it's also accepted, the guy will get killed. It's only
an עד זומם Ed Zomem question. And the question is, can you
get the first set of witnesses חייב for עדים זוממין Edim Zomemin
as well? Okay, so it's a very different type of a question.
כי פליגי באדי גניבה. חזקיה אמר אין נהרגין, Ki Peligi Be'edei Geneivah.
Chizkiyah Amar Ein Neheragin, you can't get the first set of witnesses
killed. גניבה לחודיה קאי ומכירה לחודיה קאי. Geneivah Lechudei Kai Umechirah Lechudei
Kai. They each one stands by itself, which by the way tells
us is consistent with the idea that he says you give them
lashes, that conceptually we don't see this as one big sin of
גניבה. Geneivah. Conceptually we see this as two distinct sins. So therefore
this was a completely separate court case which let us give lashes
and therefore they're Each one stands by itself which by the way
tells us that this is consistent with the idea that he says
you give them lashes, that conceptually we don't see this as one
big sin of גניבה, gneivah, conceptually we see this as two distinct
sins. So therefore this was a completely separate court case which let
us give lashes and therefore they're the ones that are the עדים
זוממים eidem zomemim for מיתה. Okay. רבי יוחנן אמר נהרגים. Rebbi Yochanan
amar neheragim. No, גניבה דאתחלתא דמכירה הוא. gneivah d'as'chalata d'mechira hu.
We view this as one big, we don't give lashes because all
of this is one big sin leading to the death penalty, it's
not two separate sins. It's one big sin leading to the death
penalty. And since it's all one big court case and one big
sin that has multiple parts that we have to prove, but ultimately
it's all one big court case, right? Therefore, these guys are also
עדים זוממים eidem zomemim and they will also get killed. Okay, is
that clear? So it's a very nice debate. If you view it
as two things, you give him lashes because this is not a
death penalty sin, but these guys then don't get killed. If you
view it as one thing, you don't give him lashes because it's
a death penalty sin, but then they're all part of the same
capital court case and the first guys will get killed as well.
Okay.
ומודה רבי יוחנן בעדים הראשונים... U'modeh Rebbi Yochanan b'eidem harishonim... Okay, you
know what, we'll just end here. Okay. Oh,
I mean I would like to finish but we're already quite over.
What?
That's part of the same thought.
I know. You want to? All right fine. Let's just give me
three more minutes. We're going to finish this baby up. Okay, so
it says like this. ומודה רבי יוחנן U'modeh Rebbi Yochanan we really
should do this.
Okay. ומודה רבי יוחנן בעדים הראשונים של בן סורר ומורה שהוזממו אין
נהרגים משום שיכולים לומר להלקותו באנו. U'modeh Rebbi Yochanan b'eidem harishonim shel
ben sorer u'moreh she'huzmemu ein neheragim mishum she-yecholim lomar l'halkoso banu. But
רבי יוחנן would agree, here he says it's all one big court
case and therefore you don't get lashes here and they're all עדים
זוממים. eidem zomemim. But here he agrees they're two distinct acts, okay?
And because they're two distinct acts, these guys do give him lashes
and these guys would not get the death penalty because they are
two distinct by the עדים זוממים. eidem zomemim. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
let's just read אמר אביי Amar Abaye since I got you going
with me this long. He wraps the whole thing up. הכל מודים
בבן סורר ומורה, Ha-kol modim b'ben sorer u'moreh, everybody will agree, חזקיה
ורבי יוחנן, Chizkiyah v'Rebbi Yochanan, there are cases that nobody gets killed.
והכל מודים בבן סורר ומורה V'ha-kol modim b'ben sorer u'moreh everybody agree
about בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh that they both get killed.
ומחלוקת בבן סורר ומורה U'machlokes b'ben sorer u'moreh and they debate בן
סורר ומורה. ben sorer u'moreh. What does it mean? הכל מודים בבן
סורר ומורה בעדים הראשונים. Ha-kol modim b'ben sorer u'moreh b'eidem harishonim. The
first ones, everybody agrees that this is a distinct case, it's not
part of this, and therefore the lashes are administered and these people
cannot be part of the death penalty. Okay. הכל מודים בבן סורר
ומורה בעדים הראשונים שהוזממו אין נהרגים משום שיכולים לומר
להלקותו באנו. Ha-kol modim b'ben sorer u'moreh b'eidem harishonim she-ein neheragim mishum
she-yecholim lomar l'halkoso banu. They're there just to give lashes, it's not
all one big sin, and therefore if they're proven זוממים zomemim they
don't get the death penalty. והכל מודים בבן סורר ומורה בעדים האחרונים
שנהרגים. V'ha-kol modim b'ben sorer u'moreh b'eidem acharonim she-neheragim. Everybody agrees that
in בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh the second ones are only
there to get him killed, so if they're lying they will be
killed. משום שהעדים הראשונים יכולים לומר להלקותו באנו והני כולה דבר קעבדי.
Mishum she-eidem harishonim yecholim lomar l'halkoso banu v'hanei kulla d'var ka-avdi. The
second ones are building on the first, the first was totally accepted
by itself, and the second ones are getting him killed. ומחלוקת בבן
סורר ומורה, U'machlokes b'ben sorer u'moreh, but they would debate בן סורר
ומורה ben sorer u'moreh in the case of, which is the case
that they would debate? שניים אומרים בפנינו גנב ושניים אומרים בפנינו אכל.
Shnayim omrim l'fanenu ganav v'shnayim omrim l'fanenu achal.
Let's say two witnesses said he stole the money and two witnesses
said he ate it. So that's a case of חצי דבר, chatzi
davar, right? Because stealing by itself is not enough unless it's combined
with the eating. So that's the classic debate of דבר ולא חצי
דבר davar v'lo chatzi davar that each one is only a partial
testimony. אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Assi, said רב אסי. Rav Assi.
עדי מכירה בנפש שהוזממו אין נהרגים משום שיכולים לומר עבדי מכרתי. Eidem
mechira b'nefesh she-huzmemu ein neheragim mishum she-yecholim lomar avdi macharti. If you
were just testified on this without these witnesses and they were lying,
they're not killed because maybe they didn't, maybe he didn't even do
a sin, maybe he was selling somebody who actually was a slave.
So that's pretty obvious. Not only are they not killed, but you
know their testimony is meaningless anyway. So the גמרא Gemara, says, אמר
רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, כמאן אזלא הא שמעתא דרב אסי כרבי
עקיבא דאמר דבר ולא חצי דבר. k'man azla ha shema'ata d'Rav Assi
k'Rebbi Akiva d'amar davar v'lo chatzi davar. That's following רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva because he says when you testify to this, you're only testifying
to a half thing. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, what
do you mean? דאית לרבנן נהרגים, De-it lerabbanan neheragim, you think according
to the Rabbis they would be killed? הא מיתוכא קאמר. Hami-tocha ka-mar.
According to the Rabbis they also wouldn't be killed. They only said
they saw him sold, they didn't even say they saw a capital
crime being committed, so of course they can't be killed. It's not
about a דבר davar or חצי דבר chatzi davar issue.
אלא אפילו תימא רבנן. Ela afilu teima Rabbanan. It's not limited to
רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. Even if you could testify on a half
thing, that's only an issue if the other half eventually got testified.
But if all you testified to was this half, okay, so then
you be, so then you didn't say anything meaningful. אלא אפילו תימא
רבנן ובדלא אתו עדי גניבה. Ela afilu teima Rabbanan u'vdelo at-o eidei
gneivah.
So if all you testified to was this half, of course these
guys wouldn't get killed, they haven't even testified that he did a
crime. Is that clear, right? Okay. אי הכי, Ee hachi, says the
גמרא, מאי למימרא? mai le-meimra? So then that's patently obvious. What else
are you, right? No. צריכא דאף על גב דאתו לבסוף. Tzricha d'af
al gav d'asu l'vasaf. No, no, here's the case. First they came
to court and they said we saw him sell this kid. Okay,
so on the face of it they said nothing. What did they
testify to? A sale of a slave. Okay? But then these witnesses
showed up and said we saw him steal... kid. So now, in
hindsight, can we say, "Ah, so we'll combine the two, and he's
חייב מיתה"? chayav misa Oh, and now it turns out you're lying,
now we'll get you to be עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. Can these
guys become עדים זוממים edim zomemim in hindsight, because after these guys
came later we now see that they were getting him killed and
they'll be חייב מיתה? chayav misa?
Well, that's going to be the question. The answer should be how
the heck do we know that they were trying to do that?
So let's take a look. וכי תימא מאי למימרא, ve-ki teima mai
lemimra, which is what you're saying, David. Okay, but if these guys
came later, these guys could plead complete innocence. Of course they can't
get no. No, צריכא דקא מרמזי רמוזי. tzericha de-ka meramze remuze.
No, no, no. They were sort of signaling to one another. These
guys came and then they said like, right? They were signaling to
these guys. So מהו דתימא, mahu de-teima, I might think רמיזה מילתא
היא, remiza milta hi,
that that's halachically significant, and when they were seen signaling that shows
that they were all in cahoots, and now that they're shown lying
we can get them killed, קא משמע לן דרמיזה לאו כלום היא,
ka mashma lan de-remiza lav klum hi, that it's not significant. So
that's interesting. If you're really smart,
you'll switch the order. You'll go first, then you'll have them come.
If you succeed, the court will combine the two and get the
guy killed, and if you don't succeed, then you can always just
claim innocence and you'll get off, even if you're seen signaling the
other witnesses. Okay, we did that a little quickly, but I think
we get the idea, so thank you for sticking with it and
we will pick up with the next משנה mishna tomorrow.